<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Gabriel Schaidhauer</title>
        <description>This is a personal blog where I can put my ideas and share with anyone interested</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 08:55:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 08:55:00 -0300</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Post exemplo</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;KV&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiking can sometimes involves bushwhacking and hiking is sometimes referred to as such. This specifically refers to difficult walking through dense forest, undergrowth, or bushes, where forward progress requires pushing vegetation aside. In extreme cases of bushwhacking, where the vegetation is so dense that human passage is impeded, a machete is used to clear a pathway. The Australian term bushwalking refers to both on and off-trail hiking. Common terms for hiking used by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Zealand&quot;&gt;New Zealanders&lt;/a&gt; are tramping (particularly for overnight and longer trips), walking or bushwalking. Trekking is the preferred word used to describe multi-day hiking in the mountainous regions of India, Pakistan, Nepal, North America, South America, Iran and in the highlands of East Africa. Hiking a long-distance trail from end-to-end is also referred to as trekking and as thru-hiking in some places. In North America, multi-day hikes, usually with camping, are referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backpacking_(wilderness)&quot;&gt;backpacking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;long-distance-hiking&quot;&gt;Long Distance Hiking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently nowadays long distance hikes (walking tours) are undertaken along long distance paths, including the National Trails in England and Wales, the National Trail System in the USA and The Grande Randonnée (France), Grote Routepaden, or Lange-afstand-wandelpaden (Holland), Grande Rota (Portugal), Gran Recorrido (Spain) is a network of long-distance footpaths in Europe, mostly in France, Belgium, the Netherlands and Spain. There are extensive networks in other European countries of long distance trails, as well as in Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Nepal, and to a lesser extent other Asiatic countries, like Turkey, Israel, and Jordan. In the Alps of Austria, Slovenia, Switzerland, Germany, France, and Italy walking tours are often made from ‘hut-to-hut’, using an extensive system of mountain huts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-full caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/ogabriel/images/mountain-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mountain&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;Norway is Beautiful&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the late 20th-century there has been a proliferation of official and unofficial long distance routes, which mean that hikers now are more likely to refer to using a long distance way (Britain), trail (USA), The Grande Randonnée (France), etc., than setting out on a walking tour. Early examples of long distance paths, include the Appalachian Trail in the USA and the Pennine Way in Britain. Pilgrimage routes are now treated, by some walkers, as long distance routes, and the route taken by the British National Trail the North Downs Way closely follows that of the Pilgrims’ Way to Canterbury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hiking times can be estimated by Naismith’s rule or Tobler’s hiking function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;equipment&quot;&gt;Equipment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The equipment required for hiking depends on the length of the hike, but day hikers generally carry at least water, food, a map, and rain-proof gear. Hikers usually wear sturdy hiking boots for mountain walking and backpacking, as protection from the rough terrain, as well as providing increased stability. The Mountaineers club recommends a list of “Ten Essentials” equipment for hiking, including a compass, sunglasses, sunscreen, a flashlight, a first aid kit, a fire starter, and a knife. Other groups recommend items such as hat, gloves, insect repellent, and an emergency blanket. A GPS navigation device can also be helpful and route cards may be used as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Returning home is the most difficult part of long-distance hiking; You have grown outside the puzzle and your piece no longer fits.”
&lt;cite&gt;― Cindy Ross&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proponents of ultralight backpacking argue that long lists of required items for multi-day hikes increases pack weight, and hence fatigue and the chance of injury. Instead, they recommend reducing pack weight, in order to make hiking long distances easier. Even the use of hiking boots on long-distances hikes is controversial among ultralight hikers, because of their weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;environmental-impact&quot;&gt;Environmental Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural environments are often fragile, and may be accidentally damaged, especially when a large number of hikers are involved. For example, years of gathering wood can strip an alpine area of valuable nutrients. and some species, such as martens or bighorn sheep, are very sensitive to the presence of humans, especially around mating season. Generally, protected areas such as parks have regulations in place to protect the environment, so as to minimize such impact. Such regulations include banning wood fires, restricting camping to established camp sites, disposing or packing out faecal matter, and imposing a quota on the number of hikers. Many hikers espouse the philosophy of Leave No Trace, following strict practices on dealing with food waste, food packaging, and other impact on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human waste is often a major source of environmental impact from hiking, and can contaminate the watershed and make other hikers ill. ‘Catholes’ dug 10 to 25 cm (4 to 10 inches) deep, depending on local soil composition and covered after use, at least 60 m (200 feet) away from water sources and trails, are recommended to reduce the risk of bacterial contamination. [ &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hiking&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; ]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/_drafts/en/key-value-databases</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/_drafts/en/key-value-databases</guid>
                
                <category>amor%en-US%</category>
                
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bancos de dados Chave e Valor</title>
                <description>&lt;p&gt;Bancos de dados chave e valor são uma categoria que abrange uma série de bancos de dados NoSQL com caracteristicas similares. Apesar disto, nem todos são iguais, aqui vou explicar um pouco algumas destas caracteriscas sem entrar a fundo nas especificidades de cada um.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para saber mais sobre a definição de um banco de dados NoSQL, as diferenças que eles tem de um banco de dados relacional sobre o teorema de CAP entre outras coisas, um ótimo livro chamado &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com.br/NoSQL-Distilled-Emerging-Polyglot-Persistence-ebook/dp/B0090J3SYW/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=&amp;amp;sr=&quot;&gt;NoSQL Distilled&lt;/a&gt;. Este livro abrange conceitos iniciais e gerais de bancos de dados NoSQL e serve como uma ótima base para quem quer aprender um pouco mais.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;como-assim-chave-e-valor&quot;&gt;Como assim chave e valor?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Um banco de dados chave valor é uma estrutura para armazenamento de dados que funciona de forma muito similar a uma estrutura de dados do tipo mapa ou um dicionário, onde nós temos uma chave. Esta chave é um identificador para um registro é como se ela guardasse o endereço para o valor que procuramos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilizando uma analogia simples, pode se dizer que uma estrutura deste tipo é como a recepção de uma pousada. Ao chegar na pousada e informar a hospedagem a recepção nos entrega uma chave e esta chave contem o numero do nosso quarto e nos permite acessá-lo. De posse desta chave sempre conseguirmos ter um acesso direto ao nosso quarto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kv-database/reception.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hotel Reception&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trazendo isto um pouco mais perto da linguagem técnica podemos pensar também em um &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-json highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;quartos&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;306&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;camas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;tv&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;plasma&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;206&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;camas&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;tv&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;plasma&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tá-mas-onde-entra-o-banco-de-dados&quot;&gt;Tá mas onde entra o banco de dados?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certo, se chegamos até aqui, provavelmente você já entendeu um pouco de como tudo isto funciona, e talvez até já tenha lidado com mapas e dicionários com algumas linguagens de programação, mas fica a pergunta, o que diabos isso tudo tem a ver com bancos de dados e o que são bancos de dados chave e valor, certo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bom tem tudo a ver e você já vai ver porquê.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De acordo com a definição da &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/br/database/what-is-database/&quot;&gt;Oracle&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Um banco de dados é uma coleção organizada de informações - ou dados - estruturadas, normalmente armazenadas eletronicamente em um sistema de computador&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nesta categoria se encaixam softwares cujo objetivo é manter dados de forma organizada:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://redis.io&quot;&gt;Redis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/dynamodb/&quot;&gt;DynamoDB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.project-voldemort.com/voldemort/&quot;&gt;Voldemort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aqui trago somente 3 exemplos de bancos chave e valor mas esta lista não tem o objetivo de de ser exaustiva, Este &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Key–value_database&quot;&gt;artigo&lt;/a&gt; possui uma lista mais completa caso seja do seu interesse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estes bancos em geral, embora não trabalhem exclusivamente como chave e valor desempenham bem este papel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bancos de dados Chave e Valor podem operar de duas formas: Em memória ou de forma híbrida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bancos-de-dados-em-memória&quot;&gt;Bancos de dados em memória&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image-card width-wide caption&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kv-database/memory.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Memory&quot; /&gt;
  
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;caption-text&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quando um banco de dados está configurado para trabalhar em memória o que ocorre é que toda a informação é armazenada na memória RAM do servidor. Como tudo, quando falamos de software (e até em outras situações) existem pontos positivos e negativos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como principal ponto positivo temos a velocidade. Bancos de dados operando exclusivamente em memória não precisam escrever a informação em disco e o acesso a memória é muito mais rápido que o acesso a disco portanto são bancos onde a escrita e a leitura de informações é muito rápida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em se tratando de bancos chave e valor a leitura de informações se torna muito rápida também pela forma como é armazenda pois similar a um mapa, a partir da chave temos acesso direto ao valor então na maior parte dos casos podemos dizer que teremos uma complexidade O(1) para a leitura de informações destes bancos de dados.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mas como &lt;a href=&quot;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_ain%27t_no_such_thing_as_a_free_lunch&quot;&gt;não existe almoço grátis&lt;/a&gt; existem também alguns lados negativos desta abordagem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como as informações estão em memória e a memória RAM é volátil, caso ocorra alguma falha, queda de energia, etc. esta informação pode ser inteiramente perdida. Outro ponto importante é que usualmente temos uma quantidade muito menor de memória RAM do que disco nos servidores, e esta não é facilmente expansivel a ponto de podermos ter memória de forma elástica, inclusive pelo seu custo, sendo assim ficamos limitados a quantidade disponível de memória RAM, portanto é preciso tomar cuidado, tanto para garantir que estamos usando esta abordagem com dados que realmente valham a pena pois não teremos muito espaço, bem como, que esta informação não represente problema caso perdida ou possa ser realimentada de outra fonte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;armazenamento-híbrido&quot;&gt;Armazenamento Híbrido&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estes bancos geralmente não trabalham somente com armazenamento em disco, especialmente visto que o objetivo deles em geral é ter ótima performance, sendo assim normalmente eles trabalham com uma abordagem mais híbrida. Esta abordagem funciona, em geral, de forma que toda informação quando é gravada é persistida no disco porém uma parte dela é mantida em memória para que o acesso seja rápido.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O que é ou não mantido em memória vai depender da política de cada banco de dados e geralmente pode ser configurada de acordo com o seu use case para definir a forma que melhor se adequa, podendo ser por exemplo os registros mais recentes, os registros mais acessados, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/_drafts/pt/key-value-databases</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/_drafts/pt/key-value-databases</guid>
                
                <category>data%pt-BR%</category>
                
                <category>nosql%pt-BR%</category>
                
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>